We're now going to look at loops in programming and obviously specifically here loops in Python.
So there are two types of loops that you will find in every single programming language available basically.
And those are for loops and while loops.
So we're going to start off by looking at for loops in this lecture.
And then we'll cover while loops in the next.
I know at first this might seem a bit confusing, but hopefully as we give some more examples and as
we go along, it will make more sense.
And of course, if you are stuck, you can always ask us questions.
So for loop basically looks like this I'm going to type it out and then I'm going to explain it to you.
So what we're saying try and think about it as a sentence for R which is a variable like we had before
for R or a number in in a range of let's say five.
We want something to happen.
So what am I actually saying here.
So what I'm saying is I'm using this keyword called for because this is a for loop.
So for a number in a range of five I want something to happen.
So basically I want something to happen over and over and over again.
And in this case I want that something to happen five times.
So I'm just going to print out to show you what is actually happening in this loop.
So again I'm saying for R in a range of five we're going to want to print something just to see what
this loop is actually doing and how loops are working.
So let's just print hello and see what happens okay.
So I'm going to run it now okay.
And what you can see basically what has happened here is hello has printed 12345 times.
So if you think about that logically it makes sense because we are loop to print a value five times.
But now what is R during this whole loop.
So every time the loop is going around and around if you remember as a variable.
So that means it I can change.
So I was actually changing every time we're going around and around and around in this loop.
So to see what our actually becomes and what value are starts to hold while the loop goes around, let's
print R.
So we're just printing this over here each time the loop goes around.
If you remember what I told you in one of our other lectures, in programming, you always count from
zero.
So you might have expected this to go one, two three, four, five.
But no, because this is programming.
We always come from zero.
So it's printed R five times, but each time the loops going around one has been added to this value
of R.
So the first time the loop went R started as zero, then the loop went again and R became one.
So it's just like counting.
So basically all this loop does here is it counts five times.
So if you wanted to do something a certain amount of times you can obviously change this number.
So let's just make this number now Out.
Eight.
So what's going to happen?
We've counted again eight times, but from 0 to 7.
Okay, so this is the simplest type of loop that you can get.
And if you can understand this then you are already well on your way to understanding loops.
But it does start to get a bit more confusing.
So now I'm going to change something in loops.
You have these things inside the brackets over here that are called parameters.
So anything inside these brackets are called parameters, which is another word that you'll have to
remember in programming.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to add another parameter.
So I'm going to add a zero.
So what I've done here now instead of just saying I want this loop to go around.
And around eight times I'm now saying I'm now giving it a starting point.
So this zero over here is telling my loop, I want you to start counting from zero and then stop counting
at eight.
But remember what I said about how programs count.
So let's run this again and you'll see it's exactly the same as what happened before.
It's run from zero, which was my starting point to eight.
But because that because programming languages count from 0 to 7, it stopped at seven.
So basically it stopped at one less than whatever this number is here.
So 0 to 7, it's run eight times but started at zero.
Okay.
But now what happens if I change this zero and I no longer want my program to start counting from zero.
I want it to start counting from.
Let's just go one, because that seems a bit more simple.
Now let's see what happens.
So again, even though now it's counting from one, it's still ending at seven over here instead of
ending at eight.
And that's again because the program still counting from zero.
We've just told it.
Oh, no.
Ignore that zero and just only print from the one.
And you can change this to any number as long as it's for now less than the the second number over here.
So we can say start counting from five.
And what is it going to do?
Five.
Six seven.
Okay.
So remember this is the number it starts at.
And it's going to end at one less than this number here okay.
Now to make things even more interesting we can add one more parameter to this for loop.
So I'm going to start it again at zero.
And now I'm going to add in a third parameter over here.
And what this one actually does is it tells my loop what to count in.
So let's say I wanted to count even numbers.
I'm going to tell the loop I want you to print every second number, which is basically the same thing
as counting in even numbers.
So what it's done here is it's printed the zero.
Then this two here said don't print the next number, only print the number after that.
In other words, print every second number.
So it's printed 0246.
Printed every second number.
So the first number again start at this end at this.
But we all know it's one less than this and count in twos.
So you would have thought okay why is it then stopped at six?
Well, obviously, because if this is ending at seven, two more then seven is eight, which it shouldn't
print.
So it's just stopped at six.
So if you think about it logically, it all really does make sense because it's starting from the zero
and ending at that seven.
Okay.
And then to make things even a bit more interesting, what we're going to do now is we're going to count
backwards.
Of course, you can change this number to counting in anything.
If I wanted to count in threes, just change it to three and it's going to start from zero and print
every third number.
And you can again change the starting number.
You can play around with it.
Okay.
But now what I'm going to do is I'm going to backspace these.
What happens if you'd like to count maybe from the biggest number and go down in descending order.
So you can also do you can also do this.
But now we have to change our ordering of our parameters around a bit.
The first number is still where it's going to start.
But of course now we want it to start with a bigger number.
So we're going to start at ten.
We want it to end at one and we want it to go backwards.
So that means this number over here needs to be negative.
So starting ending negative.
And now again you'll see it's going down 9876.
But what it's done here from ten sorry ten 9876 and so on.
It's ended at two.
So if you think about it, of course it's not going to end at the one over here, but it's going to
end at one number before the one, which in this case is two because the two came before the one.
So it's the same sort of thing.
But except now we're going backwards.
Now of course, this isn't very fun.
All we're doing is printing out.
But these come in handy a lot of the time when you want to repeat something a whole lot of times for
a certain amount of time.
So like we were saying earlier in life, you come across loops all the time.
Okay.
So that briefly is a range based for loop.
So play around with it a bit and try out different combinations.
And yeah, hopefully you start to get the hang of it.